A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    - 1806 July 29 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial issues especially those surrounding the debt and bond of Owens. Also draws up a small contract which indicates that because Smith is a resident of Maryland, that his financial issues should be settled under Maryland laws, 4 pages (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 1806 August 02 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his concern for the George Nicholas family in their time of loss; Morrison is especially concerned about their mental stability, health, and their futures, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:6)
    - 1806 August 13 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses numerous family issues especially those concerning the family of George Nicholas and what they will do in the future. Indicates that just a few days before her death, Mrs. George Nicholas withdrew $1500 from S[amuel] Smith. Inquires into whether Wilson Nicholas would ever consider moving to Kentucky. Discusses the talents of some of the children, especially Samuel's for public speaking if he had the correct education, 14 pages (Box-folder 2:7)
    - 1806 August 14 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial debts, especially that of Mr. Owings, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:8)
    - 1806 September 19 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his concerns that Georgeanna should be careful about making attachments and needs to make a good match, instead of rushing into an attachment because she wants to be away from her family. Also touches on Owings' debts, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:9)
    - 1806 October 15 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, explains that he has put George Nicholas's farm and house on the market in Kentucky and in Wilson Cary Nicholas's name. Indicates that P. [Owenby?] is very upset by the way he and his family are being treated by W.C. Nicholas who is not returning his letters, etc., 3 pages (Box-folder 2:10)
    - 1806 October 30 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the placement of George Nicholas's children and the need for them to have guardians so that the girls do not find themselves in difficult situations and the boys do not misbehave, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:11)
    - 1806 November 06 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the George Nicholas children, indicating that both Nancy and Georgeanna are engaged. He suggests that with these two married, that the estate may be able to provide for the rest comfortably and that they can collect their eleventh share when they are at least 21 years old, so that, in the case of Cary, when he turns 21 in 1807, he will be able to leave Kentucky and establish himself elsewhere, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:12)
    - 1806 December 01 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks that Wilson Nicholas appoint James Coleman, Thomas Bodley, and James Hughes to be the Attornies [sic] to Convey for both W. Nicholas and S. Smith, 1 page, enclosed broadside advertising the sale of George Nicholas's farm and land transferred to Rare Books (Broadside 1806 .V25) (Box-folder 2:13)
    - 1806 December 26 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, acknowledges the late receipt of W. Nicholas's last letter. Indicates that continued business transactions are underway, 1 page (Box-folder 2:14)
    - 1806 December 31 Samuel Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the fidelity of [General James Wilkinson?] and his relationship to the Aaron Burr Conspiracy; apparently believes Wilkinson blameless in his actions; also believes that Burr's agents have used any name that they thought would produce followers, 6 pages (Box-folder 2:15)
    - 1807 January 09 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks that Wilson Nicholas speak on behalf of Mr.[James] Hughes who would like to gain an appointment as a judge, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:16)
    - 1807 January 24 J. Nelson to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a land purchase and how the writer had been approached with a proposal but now cannot follow through with purchasing the land in Albemarle, 1 page (Box-folder 2:17)
    - 1807 February 06 Joseph C. Cabell to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], apologizes for his delayed response citing his recent marriage as being disruptive to his normal habits. Thanks W. Nicholas for some previous favor and says he need not write to Samuel Smith on his behalf, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:18)
    - 1807 February 07 S[amuel] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses information from his brother, R[obert] S[mith], about the rumored treaty with Great Britain and mentions he has left for Bermuda to claim their ship Apostle and cargo which was captured within five miles of the Cape, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:19)
    - 1807 February [08] James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, informs W. Nicholas of the sale of G. Nicholas's land, farm, and slaves for more than $37,000. Continues to discuss his concern with George Nicholas's children who still have very few assets and must rely on the welfare of wealthy friends. Argues that Owings must be forced to pay his debt to W. Nicholas so that money can be procured for the children. Suggests that Nancy should not be forced to marry in Kentucky, 21 pages (Box-folder 2:20)
    - 1807 March 02 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, continues the discussion of the George Nicholas financial issues. Mentions bonds given to Henry Clay, 7 pages (Box-folder 2:21)
    - 1807 March 07 Cary Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, expresses Cary's gratitude and affection for his uncle, Wilson Nicholas. Continues to ask for W. Nicholas's good will and wishes as Cary starts for Kentucky and a personal pursuit of law, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:22)
    - 1807 March 09 Samuel Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses the closure of the Owings bonds of $20,000 and the need to collect the vast amount of interest accumulated on that bond over the years. Suggests that both Samuel Smith and Wilson Nicholas would get at least $1120, exclusive of interest, from Owings, 1 page (Box-folder 2:23)
    - 1807 May 15 [Wilson Cary Nicholas] to [?], fragment, indicates that thirty- one stands of arms and ammunition will be given to the receiver to be distributed to the regiment, 1 page (Box-folder 2:24)
    - 1807 June 08 R[obert] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], indicates that the real conflict in the upcoming election will be between James Madison and George Clinton and that southern prejudices will definitely play a part in this election. Suggests that Congress has a majority of Republicans which are favorable to Madison. Closes by saying that the current international climate will impact the election as well with both England and Spain harassing the United States, 5 pages (Box-folder 2:25)
    - 1807 June 29 R[obert] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], briefly discusses familial issues and then moves to the upcoming presidential election. Speaks of the outrage on the frigate Chesapeake making it difficult to preserve peaceful relations with Great Britain. Indictments for treason have been found against Burr, Blennerhassett, Dayton, John Smith, Senator of Ohio, Tyler, and Floyd. Describes the details of the Leapard-Chesapeake affair. Spends some time in considering the 'sic volo' ['Thus I will'] of D.C. [DeWitt Clinton?] and other possible eventualities in the election, 5 pages (Box-folder 2:26)
    - 1807 July 04 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, informs that $3,000 "at ten days sight" will be sent to John Smith, esq., 4 pages (Box-folder 2:27)
    - 1807 July 07 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, follows up on Morrison's last letter regarding a draft for $3000 to John Smith, 1 page (Box-folder 2:28)
    - 1807 July 20 R[obert] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas ?], writes that although the advice in his letter was sound and was read by several department heads and the President, it has not been adopted. He discusses a letter from Armstrong explaining the recent arming of Austria who plans engineering an armed mediation, "its object is a separate peace between France, Russia, Prussia, and Sweden, leaving the field of battle to France and England. In such case the commerce and manufactures of G[reat] B[ritain] will be excluded from the North of Europe - from the Med[iterranean] - from Turkey - and if to this list American be added - the downfall of G[reat] B[ritain] may be pronounced as a certainty." Smith believes now is the time for the United States to insist on its rights and privileges as a neutral power and join the powers of Europe to resist the tyranny of the seas by the British. But he says "To any such course however Mr. Jefferson and Mr. Madison are [greatly] averse. Skilled as they both are in the use of the pen, they presume altogether upon its powers." A British vessel has withdrawn from Hampton Roads, Virginia, to Lynn Haven Bay, Florida, but he expects more examples of arrogance from the British fleet. Smith approves the actions of the people of Norfolk who have erected guns on their fort., 7 pages (Box-folder 2:29)
    - 1807 August 24 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his business troubles resulting from the actions of the British fleet against his commercial vessels, especially those trading in India; notes that General James Wilkinson is concerned that he might be implicated in the Burr Conspiracy but according to Smith "I have little fear for the Integrity of his Character - that he may have been indiscreet I can easily believe - that in the Confidence of long friendship and a high very high opinion of Burr he may have said [or even?] written things that may require explanation. I can believe but that he has ever harbored a dishonorable Intention against the Interest or the fidelity he owed his country, I neither can nor will believe." Smith supposes the judge intends on stopping the trial of Burr for treason and permit the jury to find him guilty of a misdemeanor instead. Gives information concerning a French pirate who has been terrorizing the Chesapeake Bay near Baltimore, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:30)
    - 1807 September 13 William Berkeley to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses a $300 payment, 1 page (Box-folder 2:31)
    - 1807 October 11 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Cary Nicholas and his dislike for law work in Kentucky, compounded by his tendency to be idle. He also discusses other possible occupations., 4 pages (Box-folder 2:32)
    - 1807 October 11 T[homas] M[ann] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses money due Nicholas and other issues pertaining to the Trist estate. Closes with a long direct quote from President [Jefferson] concerning the actions of the British Foreign Secretary, George Canning, who "sent Monroe a copy of our proclamation & enquired into its authenticity in such a way as showed they meant to construe it into a disrespect if not an hostility.", 3 pages (Box-folder 2:33)
    - 1807 November 09 Geo[rge?] F. Jefferson to Wilson Cary Nicholas, gives information concerning two bonds from Benjamin Childress for £244.26 each. Also discusses W. Nicholas's tobacco sales, 1 page (Box-folder 2:34)
    - 1807 November 15 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [James Morrison], writes about the birth of a daughter delaying his return to Congress, indicates that General [Samuel] Smith does not think that contracts can be made but at a low price, and recommends that he ship five hundred barrels of his pork to [Baltimore?], on consignment, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:35)
    - 1807 December 13 William H. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, thanks Nicholas for his letter, assures him that he agrees with the ideas expressed by Nicholas, and promises to write more soon, 1 page (Box-folder 2:36)
    - 1808 February 06 Joshua Fry to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses some financial difficulties and possible solutions, indicates that he hopes to meet in Philadelphia or Baltimore in the coming months, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:37)
    - 1808 March 05 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a financial transaction drawn up between W. Nicholas and Taylor. Randolph writes Nicholas to warn him that Taylor may not be the most trustworthy but that he will do everything possible to secure the venture; believes three-fourths of Virginia will go for James Madison, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:38)
    - 1808 March 19 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses some financial business with which W. Nicholas and Samuel Smith have both been negligent. Indicates that a loan for $3000 will need to be returned within the next few months. Accuses Nicholas and Smith of being negligent in regard to the children of George Nicholas. Inquires about Margaretta, 4 pages (Box-folder 2:39)
    - 1808 March 20 James Morrison to Robert Smith (Secretary of the Navy), discusses a shipment of 50 or 60 tons of round 24 and 32 pound balls manufactured by Thomas Deye Owings (1776-1853), [Lexington, Kentucky?] to be delivered to New Orleans for the Department of the Navy in the next several weeks. Mr. Owings would like Smith to draft the payment to Wilson Cary Nicholas in order to repay Owings's debt to Nicholas, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:40)
    - 1808 August 12 Theodore Armistead to Wilson Cary Nicholas, [enclosed are Edward Antill's direction for manufacturing hemp], includes a short letter that introduces the directions for hemp and makes some pleasantries, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:41)
    - 1808 August 25 Doctor [Charles] Everett to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses which of the several mineral springs would be best for his complaints, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:42)
    - 1808 October 23 Edmund Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses various legal and financial matters concerning Nicholas, 1 page (Box-folder 2:43)
    - 1808 December 21 Peggy Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas [her husband], describes a slave uprising that had been planned for the 25 th of December but which had been foiled. The three culprits are to be hanged. She then entreats her husband to move the family out of 'this land of terror', where she cannot live, to Lexington which she believes would be safer from domestic and foreign enemies, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:44)
    - 1808 December 26 Joseph C. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, answers a question posed by Nicholas, "I should prefer a foreign to a civil war. If there be any prospect of the efficacy of the embargo & non- intercourse as [?] measures, I should still be inclined to give scope to their action. Of this, you are more competent to decide at Washington, than we are here." Cabell believes that the United States should prepare for war in case it should come. Peace would always be preferable because "the embargo deprives our enemies of the trade of only one country, but us of that of the whole world." Cabell also discusses a letter from Mr. Yancey which states that all the delegates from [John Randolph of Roanoke ?]'s district have urged him to oppose Randolph in the next election. "Randolph's conduct seems to inspire general disgust. The common remark is, he makes mischief wherever he is, & it is time for him to stay at home.", 3 pages (Box-folder 2:45)
    - 1809 March 15 John Taylor of Caroline to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], writes, "As our friendship is irrecoverably dissolved" he is claiming his debt made by Nicholas in 1802 to be paid in two months, 1 page (Box-folder 2:46)
    - 1809 June 07 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [John Taylor of Caroline], sends a note for $14,233.33 to cover the loan from Taylor plus interest. He thanks him for the loan of the money when it was needed for such a length of time. He defends himself from Taylor's belief that he was the one who supplied information used in [Thomas?] Ritchie's attacks upon Taylor, "My feelings upon this subject are such that it is impossible I could ever have directly or indirectly 'supplied the allusions' that could have induced Mr. Ritchie or any other person to attack you. Your suspicion that 'the grounds of a part of Ritchie's scurrility flowed to him' out of your letters to me is most unjust. I affirm to you that it did not.", 2 pages (Box-folder 2:47)
    - 1809 July 15 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Owings and his attitude toward Morrison because of the unpaid debt. The letter also discusses the financial arrangements concerning George Nicholas, Cary Nicholas, Samuel Smith, and Henry Clay, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:48)
    - 1809 October 08 J. W. Hollins to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses the election results in Virginia with which he is happy, especially the re-election of their friend. Does not know what he will do with Mr. Jackson. They have received news from Nicholas's son, Robert, and many other vessels in the Mediterranean., 2 pages (Box-folder 2:49)
    - 1809 November 02 Ed[mund] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses some business matters and some issues of politics. Informs Nicholas of the recent stroke suffered by his wife., 2 pages (Box-folder 2:50)
    - 1810 January 08 Philip N. Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses business and land transactions, 8 pages (Box-folder 2:51)
    - 1810 February 06 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses various business and commerce transaction, including the trade of hemp. Briefly mentions Nicholas's service in Congress, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:52)
    - 1810 March 13 D[abney] Carr to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses land transactions, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:53)
    - 1810 March 17 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses land deals and how everything is finally sorting out in regard to them. Includes a brief discussion of how Congress could not agree on Macon's Bill and so it has been passed to the Senate, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:54)
    - 1810 March 18 Thomas Taylor to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a note owed by Nicholas for £2000 and expects a payment of at least five thousand dollars so that he can pay his own debts and go to Kentucky in the spring, 1 page (Box-folder 2:55)
    - 1810 April 13 J.W. Hollins to Wilson Cary Nicholas, mentions the operation on Margaretta's throat; gloomy accounts of commerce from both Italy and France; discusses the implication of the continued war between Great Britain and France; has just read a newspaper at the coffee house concerning numerous arrivals in England from the [West Indies] direct, several from this port [Baltimore], 3 pages (Box-folder 2:56)
    - 1810 May 23 J. Mason to Wilson Cary Nicholas, notice of receipt of letter with one hundred dollars on account for his commission, 1 page (Box-folder 2:57)
    - 1810 May 25 W[illia]m Patterson to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a debt of $5,975 that includes the principle and the interest owed on it. Patterson is unable to grant an extension of the loan due to the slowness of business, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:58)
    - 1810 May 25 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the destruction of a letter to Mr. Madison from Nicholas which would be improper to pass through Smith's hands concerning an appointment for John. He believes that President James Madison's approach to filling diplomatic posts differs from his predecessors, "they wanted to educate men to fill diplomatic appointments - he wants to enable the minister to draw the salary, his own being insufficient.", 2 pages (Box-folder 2:59)
    - 1810 June 23 [?] Lee to Wilson Cary Nicholas, inquires about the military service and other biographical information about Samuel Smith, 1 page (Box-folder 2:60)
    - 1810 July 21 J. W. Hollins to Wilson Cary Nicholas, talks about the price of wheat, the future account for England, and briefly deals with other financial transactions, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:61)
    - 1810 August 22 J. W. Hollins to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that the prices are good for wheat. Contains brief financial discussion and discussions of the travel plans of Robert Nicholas, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:62)
    - 1810 October 13 M[argaretta] Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks for some monetary help for her husband, [Norborne?], who is worried about his financial difficulties, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:63)
    - 1810 October 14 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Samuel Smith, declines an invitation for his daughter, Cary Ann, to winter with Smith and his family, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:64)
    - 1811 January 20 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that Robert Gamble of Richmond is willing to take the loan of $3000 at 10 days sight, 1 page (Box-folder 2:65)
    - 1811 January 22 W[illiam] H. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks that Nicholas proceed to ask Mr. Patterson to procure two of the iron mould board plows and forward them to Robert Gamble. Thanks Nicholas for his advice on wheat and requests any extra seed that Nicholas may have around. He also refers to the advice of [John Hartwell] Cocke of sowing hemp on some of his land, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:66)
    - 1811 February 06 John Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], apologizes for any discomfort that his previous letter might have caused when he wrote about not receiving an answer to a previous letter from Nicholas concerning his daughters, and, as he has heard Nicholas is disgusted with politics, he will not discuss either business or politics, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:67)
    - 1811 April 19 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Samuel Preston, indicates that do to various reason he is currently to repay money to Preston and Smith, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:68)
    - 1811 April 22 Wilkins & Robinson, Pittsburgh to R.C. Nicholas [corrected on address to W. C. Nicholas], earlier reply lost through a mail robbery thirty miles away, responds to a previous inquiry about whether it is better to ship hemp through New Orleans or Pittsburgh; Wilkins & Robinson assures him it is more efficient to ship through Pittsburg and offers his services, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:69)
    - 1811 April 24 Edmund Randolph to Thomas M. Randolph, asks Randolph to take the money owed him from the estate of T.M. Randolph's father and pay it to his account with Doctor Wardlaw, for fifty dollars of medicine furnished to Edmund and his wife, 1 page (Box-folder 2:70)
    - 1811 September 23 [Lt. Governor George William] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, responds to a letter which Nicholas wrote about facilitating connections between the eastern and western waterways of the state. Smith indicates that such decisions are to be made by the Executive and not the Legislature, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:71)
    - 1811 September 29 Nelson Nicholas to his uncle, Wilson Cary Nicholas, requests Wilson's approval with his plan to accompany William Rives to Williamsburg to attend college and study mathematics for as Nelson puts it, a man without knowledge of mathematics is ignorant in all things. The letter continues to explain that Nelson will still plan on studying law but will do so after finishing his college work. And indicates that he believes that he can counteract any negative impulses that he is exposed to in college, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:72)
    - [1811] November 18 Nelson Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], indicates his safe arrival to Williamsburg and his arrangements for lodging while in college which are more expensive than he originally thought they would be. Has yet to start attending law lectures and doubts that he will be able to do so until mid-December, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:73)
    - 1811 November 20 Samuel Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the likelihood that America will declare war on Great Britain for commercial reasons which Smith does not endorse but understands as Great Britain's trade embargo hurts many Americans, especially because of the price of certain goods such as wheat, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:74)